DOUGLAS L. NEVILLE

7001 Interbay blvd unit 101 ~ Tampa, Florida 33616

(253) 720-2168

doug neville@hotmail.com

COMBAT CONTROLLER

Retired U.S. Air Force Combat Controller and Joint Terminal Attack Controller (JTAC) providing expert flight following, enroute routing, terminal approach control and controlled approach services under the most demanding of operational conditions, including combat behind enemy lines. Highly organized with a proven ability to manage multiple projects, tasks and priorities effectively and in a timely manner. Superior communicator; highly effective at all organizational levels. Core competencies include:

- ◆ Top Secret/SCI Clearance ◆
- Mentoring & Training
- ♦ International Experience
- ◆ Team Player/Team Leader
- ♦ Sets Performance Standards ◆
- ♦ Innovative Problem Solver ◆
- ♦ Multi-Tasker
- Quality Assurance
 - Excellent People Skills

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Seasoned Joint Terminal Attack Controller: Proven team leadership skills combined with operational deployments to Iraq, Afghanistan and the Horn of Africa in support of Joint Special Operations Command ground forces. Career highlighted by success and continued achievement.

- Provided terminal guidance for five Special Forces teams and three partner forces in Afghanistan to resolve 20+ troops-in-contact situations for six enemy combatants captured and 39 EKIA.
- Mission planning critical to the success of eight Direct Action raids against armed Iraqi insurgents and the apprehension of four high-level enemy combatants.
- Deployed into non-permissive environments using static line and military freefall parachute techniques, SCUBA and other covert infiltration methods.
- Carried out terminal guidance for Special Forces teams and 100+ elite Iraqi forces.
- Provided combined inter-service coordination that ensured priority mission essential tasks training was incorporated into joint/combined exercises and exchange training.
- Strictly ensured that all flight control was conducted in full accordance with military, FAA, ICAO, and host nation rules & regulations.

<u>Leadership & Supervision:</u> A superior leader with demonstrated performance in high-pressure environments. Improved organizational performance through hands-on training and a leadership approach that emphasized decision-making through active listening.—

- Managed, supervised and trained 54+ apprentice JTACs in the integration of all close air support assets to include artillery and naval gunfire in joint and combined ground forces operations.
- Instructed other DOD branches and allied countries in Foreign Internal Defense (FID), interoperability and Special Tactics (ST) procedures.
- Identified requirements for planning and coordinating contingency deployments and joint combined exchange training for a 130-person Special Tactics (ST) Squadron.
- Developed and maintained lesson plans to support unique training opportunities; managed the squadron's Standards & Evaluations program; renowned for professional expertise.

<u>Problem-Solving & Analysis:</u> Consistently implements keen analytical abilities and a proven team-based work dynamic with a systems-oriented approach to facilitate efficient and effective solutions. A critical thinker open to alternative views to optimize decision-making.

- Established and maintained a trend analysis program and provided improvement strategies.
- Planned and led three mission exercises integrating joint operations with multiple air platforms as the air-to-ground interface crucial for mission success.

Continued ...

Douglas L. Neville Résumé / Page 2

EMPLOYMENT

U.S. AIR FORCE, Various Duty Stations including Iraq & Afghanistan Noncommissioned Officer-in-Charge, Weapons & Tactics Flight, 2009 – 2011 Noncommissioned Officer-in-Charge, 22 STS Blue Team, 2007 – 2009 Combat Control Craftsman / Vehicle Operations Craftsman, 1994 – 2007

1994 - 2013

EDUCATION & TRAINING

BRANDMAN UNIVERSITY, Irvine, California *Bachelor of Arts, Psychology*, 2011

COMMUNITY COLLEGE OF THE AIR FORCE, Maxwell AFB, Alabama Associate of Arts, Airway Science, 2005 Associate of Arts, Applied Science, 2005

<u>Certifications</u>: Emergency Medical Technician Washington State Certification, National Registry of Emergency Medical Technicians (NREMT) Registry No. E3089535

Awarded *Air Force Specialty Code 1C271, Combat Control Craftsman,* concurrent with these equivalent civilian job descriptions as defined by the Dept. of Labor's Dictionary of Occupational Titles (DOT), the Occupational Information Network (ONET), and the Occupational Employment Statistics (OES):

- Airplane Dispatchers and Air Traffic Controllers (OES 39002)
- Air-Traffic-Control Specialist, Tower (DOT 193.162-018)
- Chief Controller (DOT 193.167-010)
- Command and Control Center Specialists (ONET 55-3015.00)

<u>Other Air Force Specialty Codes / Additional Skill Identifiers</u>: 2T171 – Vehicle Operations Craftsman; J – Parachutist

Selected Military Training: Military Freefall Parachutist Course; Military Free Fall Jumpmaster; Military Freefall Jumpmaster (2E-F56/011-F15); Special Force Combat Dive Qualification; USAF NCO Academy; Combat Control Orientation Course; Airman Leadership School; Combat Control Static Line Jumpmaster Course; Military Free Fall Parachutist; Special Forces Combat Diver Qualification; Combat Control Apprentice Course (Enlist and Officer); Combat Survival Training Course; Airborne; Combat Control Team Screening Program

Computer Skills: MS Office Suite (Word, PowerPoint, Excel, Access)

SELECTED AWARDS

Bronze Star Medal with Valor Device (x2), Purple Heart

MILITARY

Master Sergeant (E-7), U.S. Air Force (Retired)

REFERENCES

Excellent references furnished upon request.